And how about the oil, gas and mining companies? Okay, maybe it's a bit of a cliché to talk about them. Corruption in that sector, no surprise. There's corruption everywhere, so why focus on that sector? Well, because there's a lot at stake. In 2011, natural resource exports outweighed aid flows by almost 19 to one in Africa, Asia and Latin America. Nineteen to one. Now that's a hell of a lot of schools and universities and hospitals and business startups, many of which haven't materialized and never will because some of that money has simply been stolen away. Now let's go back to the oil and mining companies, and let's go back to Dan Etete and that $1 billion deal. And now forgive me, I'm going to read the next bit because it's a very live issue, and our lawyers have been through this in some detail and they want me to get it right. Now, on the surface, the deal appeared straightforward. Subsidiaries of Shell and Eni paid the Nigerian government for the block. The Nigerian government transferred precisely the same amount, to the very dollar, to an account earmarked for a shell company whose hidden owner was Etete. Now, that's not bad going for a convicted money launderer. And here's the thing. After many months of digging around and reading through hundreds of pages of court documents, we found evidence that, in fact, Shell and Eni had known that the funds would be transferred to that shell company, and frankly, it's hard to believe they didn't know who they were really dealing with there. Now, it just shouldn't take these sorts of efforts to find out where the money in deals like this went. I mean, these are state assets. They're supposed to be used for the benefit of the people in the country. But in some countries, citizens and journalists who are trying to expose stories like this have been harassed and arrested and some have even risked their lives to do so. And finally, well, there are those who believe that corruption is unavoidable. It's just how some business is done. It's too complex and difficult to change. So in effect, what? We just accept it. But as a campaigner and investigator, I have a different view, because I've seen what can happen when an idea gains momentum. In the oil and mining sector, for example, there is now the beginning of a truly worldwide transparency standard that could tackle some of these problems. In 1999, when Global Witness called for oil companies to make payments on deals transparent, well, some people laughed at the extreme naiveté of that small idea. But literally hundreds of civil society groups from around the world came together to fight for transparency, and now it's fast becoming the norm and the law. Two thirds of the value of the world's oil and mining companies are now covered by transparency laws. Two thirds. So this is change happening. This is progress. But we're not there yet, by far. Because it really isn't about corruption somewhere over there, is it? In a globalized world, corruption is a truly globalized business, and one that needs global solutions, supported and pushed by us all, as global citizens, right here. Thank you. (Applause)
¿Y qué tal el petróleo, el gas y las empresas mineras? Bueno, tal vez es un tanto cliché hablar de ellas. La corrupción en ese sector, no es una sorpresa. Hay corrupción en todas partes, así que, ¿por qué centrarse en ese sector? Bueno, porque hay mucho en juego. En 2011, las exportaciones de recursos naturales sobrepasaron en casi 19 veces los flujos de ayuda en África, Asia y América Latina. 19 a 1. Eso es un montón de escuelas, universidades, hospitales y empresas nacientes, muchas de los cuales nunca se materializaron y jamás lo harán porque simplemente parte de ese dinero ha sido robado. Ahora volvamos al petróleo y a las empresas mineras, y vayamos a Dan Etete y el trato de mil millones. Perdónenme, voy a leer el siguiente fragmento porque es un tema muy vivo y nuestros abogados han pasado en esto con cierto detalle y quieren que lo haga bien. Ahora, en la superficie, el trato parecía sencillo. Filiales de Shell y Eni pagaron al gobierno Nigeriano por el bloque. El gobierno Nigeriano transfirió precisamente la misma cantidad, cada dólar, a una cuenta destinada de una empresa fantasma cuyo propietario oculto era Etete. No está mal para un lavador de dinero condenado. Y aquí está la cosa. Después de muchos meses de explorar y la lectura de cientos de páginas del expediente, se encontraron pruebas de que, de hecho, Shell y Eni habían sabido que los fondos se transferirían a la empresa fantasma, y francamente, es difícil creer que no sabían con quién realmente estaban lidiando allí. Ahora, no solo se debe hacer este tipo de esfuerzos para averiguar a dónde fue el dinero en negocios como éste. Es decir, son recursos del Estado. Se supone que se utilizarán para el beneficio del pueblo en su país. Pero en algunos países, los ciudadanos y periodistas que están intentando exponer historias como esta han sido hostigados y detenidos y algunos incluso han arriesgado sus vidas por hacerlo. Por último, hay quienes creen que la corrupción es inevitable. Que es así como se hacen los negocios. Que es demasiado complejo y difícil de cambiar. En efecto, ¿qué? Solo lo aceptamos. Pero como activista e investigadora, tengo una visión diferente, porque he visto lo que puede suceder cuando una idea cobra impulso. En el petróleo y el sector minero, por ejemplo, ahora hay el comienzo de un estándar de transparencia mundial real que podría abordar algunos de estos problemas. En 1999, cuando Global Witness llamó a las compañías petroleras a hacer acuerdos transparentes, algunas personas se rieron de la gran ingenuidad de esa simple idea. Pero literalmente cientos de grupos de la sociedad civil de todo el mundo, se unieron para luchar por la transparencia, y ya se está convirtiendo en la norma y la ley. Dos terceras partes del valor del petróleo y las compañías mineras del mundo se encuentran ahora cubiertas por leyes de transparencia. Dos terceras partes. Este cambio esta ocurriendo. Esto es progreso. Pero no hemos terminado; falta mucho. Porque realmente no se trata de la corrupción en algún lugar por ahí, ¿verdad? En un mundo globalizado, la corrupción es un negocio que está en todas partes y que necesita soluciones mundiales, apoyadas y empujadas por todos nosotros, como ciudadanos del mundo, aquí mismo. Gracias. (Aplausos)